Ed Lee Gossett Papers, Inclusive: 1935-1953, Bulk: 1945-1951.
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials
Ed Lee Gossett Papers
Inclusive: 1935-1953, Bulk: 1945-1951.
Baylor University, Baylor Collections of Political Materials http://www.baylor.edu/lib/bcpm/
49
Gossett, Ed Lee, 1902-1990
17 document boxes
The Congressional papers of U. S. Representative Ed Lee Gossett.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Ed Lee Gossett (1902-1990) represented Texas’s Thirteenth Congressional District from 1939 until his resignation in 1951. Although a Democrat himself, Gossett frequently opposed the policies of the New Deal wing of his own party. Gossett served as chairman for the Committee on Elections No. 2 and as member of the Immigration and Naturalization Committee. Later, as a member of the House Judiciary Committee, Gossett championed legislation restricting immigration quotas, securing state ownership of tidelands, and equalizing national railroad freight rates. He also worked with Senator Henry Cabot Lodge to introduce a constitutional amendment revising the Electoral College on a proportional system following the contentious election of Truman over Dewey in 1950.
Gossett, born January 27, 1902, moved with his parents from his birthplace, a sawmill camp called Yellow Pine located near Many, Sabine Parish in Louisiana, to a farm near Henrietta in Clay County, Texas in 1908. He attended public schools and then graduated in 1924 with a Bachelor of Arts, and subsequently in 1927 with a Bachelor of Laws from the University of Texas at Austin. After acceptance to the Texas Bar Association in 1927, he practiced law in Vernon, Texas, and served as district attorney of the Forty-sixth Judicial district from 1933 to 1937. In 1937, he moved to Wichita Falls and in 1938, was elected to the Seventy-sixth Congress on the Democratic ticket defeating pro-New Dealer W. D. McFarlane.
Throughout his career Gossett demonstrated interest in restricting immigration. His efforts culminated in his national and publicly strident opposition, beginning in 1946 and ending only with his resignation, to the Truman administration’s efforts to increase immigration quotas for displaced persons. Gossett not only sought to oppose this increase, but introduced bills reducing existing immigration quotas by half. Beginning in 1948 and until 1951, Gossett found himself also opposing the Truman administration in the Texas Tidelands Controversy. In addition to his public opposition, Gossett worked within his committee to secure the passage of several bills, including his own, recognizing state ownership of tidelands. This activity included maneuvering all tidelands bills to his subcommittee and doing “most of the leg work.” Because of his significant legislative role in the controversy, Gossett also corresponded with Price Daniel about Texas’s case in the Supreme Court on the same issue in order to coordinate efforts on both fronts.
In addition to these two prominent roles, Gossett worked on issues involving infrastructure, supply, and pricing in the oil industry, and on the equalization of national railroad freight rates to the Official Zone both during and following World War II. Furthermore, he took an interest in and publicly spoke on two significant events in the post-war worldDLCommunism and the partition of Palestine. In July 1951, Gossett resigned his congressional office and resumed private practice as the general attorney for the Texas Southwestern Bell Telephone Co., and also served as Judge of Criminal District Court in Dallas, Texas. Gossett died on November 6, 1990.
Scope and Content
The Ed Lee Gossett Papers span 1935-1953, and consist of seven linear feet of correspondence, speeches, congressional documents, reports, publications, and newspaper clippings. The bulk of the material documents the years 1945-1951, Gossett’s last three terms in office, and derives from Gossett’s legislative interests in the post-World War II Congresses in which he played several visible roles. These interests included the oil industry, interstate freight rates, Communism, and the UN and US policies toward the Palestinian partition, but most importantly immigration of displaced persons in post-war Europe and the Texas tidelands conflict. These last two subjects make up the bulk of the materials. Many of the materials on the other topics take the form of publications like magazines, weeklies, or newspaper articles and advertisements.
Aside from describing Gossett’s legislative activities, the collection also provides insight into some American attitudes toward all these issues through Gossett’s congressional correspondence and the numerous newspaper clippings, magazines, and other publications comprising the collection. Indeed, anti-Semitic sentiment pervades the topics of immigration, Communism, Palestine, and race relations, documenting this aspect of American thought during the post-war period. The collection contains little on personal matters. Materials on immigration chronicle Gossett’s legislative activities and nationally visible stance to reduce immigration quotas and oppose immigration of displaced persons while serving on congressional committees for immigration and naturalization from 1943-1951. They document his opposition to what became the 1948 Displaced Persons Act, as well as the fight to introduce tougher qualifications for immigration which eventually led to the passage of the Internal Security Act of 1950. The Tidelands series comprises information about the conflict between states and the national government over the control of submerged lands following the 1947 Supreme Court ruling in US v. California. It includes correspondence and publications documenting the battle from the states’, particularly Texas’s, perspective; statements before the Senate and House Judiciary Committees and their related bills; and filings with the Supreme Court.
Arrangement
Prior to this finding aid, the Ed Lee Gossett Papers were roughly organized into seven series titled Immigration/Displaced persons, Palestine, Communism, Interstate freight rate legislation, Tidelands, Oil industry, and General, and an inventory existed. During processing, a new series arrangement was imposed.The final arrangement has eight series: 1. General, 2. Communism, 3. Immigration, 4. Interstate Freight, 5. Oil Industry, 6. Palestine, 7. Race Relations, and 8. Tidelands.
Series 3, 7, and 8 also contain subseries. Series 3 on Immigration contains General, Correspondence, Immigration and Naturalization Service, and Immigration and Naturalization Committees. Series 7 on Palestine contains General, American Attitudes, Middle East Relations, and United Nations Partition. Series 8 on Tidelands contains General, Bills and Resolutions, Cases, Committee Hearings, and Correspondence.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the W. R. Poage Legislative Library in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 49. Acquired 1989-09-11
Related Resources
Related references
Ed Lee Gossett Papers, Accession # 49, Baylor Collections of Political Materials, W. R. Poage Legislative Library, Baylor University.
“Gossett, Ed Lee.” Biographical Directory of the United States Congress. Accessed June 9, 2015.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Gossett, Ed Lee, 1902-1990 -- Archives.
Subjects (Organizations)
United States. Congress. House.
Places
Palestine -- Relations -- United States.; United States -- Relations -- Palestine.
Subjects
Antisemitism -- United States.; Emigration and immigration law -- United States.; Freight and freightage -- Rates -- United States.; Legislators -- United States -- Archives.; Petroleum in submerged lands -- United States.; Petroleum law and legislation -- United States.; Refugees -- Government policy -- United States.; Refugees -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees -- United States.
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Legislative materials.; Maps.; Speeches.
- General, 1925-1951; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Along with materials such as maps, newsletters, pamphlets, newspaper clippings, and speeches by Gossett and others, this series contains a 1940 brief on the Brazos River Conservation; some pamphlets and letters on the electoral college; and pamphlets, letters, and speeches on US labor laws.
  - General, 1939-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - General, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brazos River Conservation, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Electoral College, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Labor, 1945-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Labor, Speeches, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Speeches, 1925-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Speeches, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal, Photographs, 1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Communism, 1945-1951; 2
  This series contains letters and publications which illustrate early reactions of some Americans to spreading Communism and the nascent Cold War. The materials contain accusations of Jewish involvement in spreading Communism and also denunciations against American officials for weak actions against Communism at home and abroad in the form of periodicals, pamphlets, open letters, and articles.
  - General, 1946-1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - General, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Anti-Jewish Publications, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Anti-Jewish Publications, 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Anti-Jewish Publications, 1948-1950 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Anti-Jewish Publications, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Common Sense, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1947-1951 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Foreign Policy and American Leadership, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Foreign Policy and American Leadership, 1951-1953 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Legislative Library Information, 1948-1951 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Rosenberg, Anna M., 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Socialism, 1939-1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Socialism, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Immigration, 1943-1951; 3
  This series relates to Gossett's activities towards immigration. Much of the material consists of correspondence to Gossett, especially after his 1946 public opposition to Truman, and provides insight into trends in American thought toward displaced persons, as well as Gossett's own views on displaced persons. While the majority of Gossett’s attention was directed toward displaced persons from Europe, his activities on the House Immigration and Naturalization Committee and later subcommittee of the Judiciary Committee included other immigration issues such as Chinese immigration and merchant marine seaman naturalization during World War II. Publications dealing with these issues are located in the "General" subseries, while correspondence on specific cases/individuals is located in the subseries dedicated to Gossett’s committee activities. Some correspondence and publications dealt with the influx of displaced persons following World War II (1945-1951), based on a narrow issue such as Jewish or German immigrants or the accentuation of housing difficulties after World War II. Correspondence dealing primarily with these topics rather than displaced persons are found in the "General" subseries. The series also records Gossett's legislative activities through bills and draft copies, hearings, public addresses, and committee correspondence, as well as Gossett's other activities on immigration committees including reports on the US Immigration and Naturalization Service.
  - General, 1943-1951; 1
    This subseries contains Gossett’s speeches, including several national radio addresses, on immigration laws arranged in date order. It begins with an undated draft (circa 1943) of a speech supporting his bill to eliminate the Chinese Exclusion Act and ends with a 1949 speech in opposition to increasing DP quotas. It comprises letters referencing specific issues in immigration (Chinese, German, Jewish, seamen naturalization, housing problems, and Canada) excluding references to the broader immigration situation. It also contains publications, news releases, and newspaper clippings about the immigration of displaced persons during the years 1945-1949.
    - General, 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Bills, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Bills, 1947-1949 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Canada, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Chinese Immigration, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - German Immigration, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Housing Problems, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Jewish Immigration, 1943-1951 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Pamphlets, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Publications and News Releases, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Seaman Naturalization, 1945-1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Speeches, 1943-1946 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Speeches, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Speeches, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Clippings, General, 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Clippings, Gossett, 1947-1949 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1949; 2
    Gossett’s correspondence on immigration begins with letters from March to November 1943 about his work to repeal the Chinese Exclusion Act. In 1945, the correspondence shifts to Gossett’s bills restricting immigration of aliens formerly serving in enemy armed forces and an overall reduction in immigration quotas, and to his growing stance against immigration of displaced persons. However, the bulk of correspondence deals with the immigration of displaced persons following World War II. Correspondence in the years 1946-1948 responds to Gossett's public addresses, while that in 1949 deals primarily with the Displaced Persons Act of 1948 and disaffection with its application toward different groups. Different correspondents provide views on its application to German, Greek, Jewish, and Baltic refugees. Letters dealing primarily with German or Jewish immigration can be found in the “General” series while letters only including these topics among others or as part of a larger criticism of the Displaced Persons Act are found here.
    - Letters, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Letters, 1943 March-July (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Letters, 1943 August-November (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Letters, 1944 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Letters, 1945 April-July (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Letters, 1945 August-November (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Letters, 1946 February-July (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Letters, 1946 August 17-19 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Letters, 1946 August 20 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Letters, 1946 August 21-30 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Letters, 1946 September-November (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 1948 January (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 1948 February (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Letters, 1948 March (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Letters, 1948 April (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Letters, 1948 May (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Letters, 1948 June (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Letters, 1948 July-December (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Letters, 1949 January (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Letters, 1949 February (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Letters, 1949 March (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Letters, 1949 April (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Letters, 1949 May (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Letters, 1949 June 1-19 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letters, 1949 June 20-30 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Letters, 1949 July (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letters, 1949 August (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letters, 1949 September (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letters, 1949 October (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Letters, 1949 November (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Immigration and Naturalization Committees, 1943-1951; 3
    This subseries relates to Gossett’s activities on the House Immigration and Naturalization Committee (1943-1945) and the House Judiciary Committee’s Subcommittee on Immigration and Naturalization (1945-1951). Correspondence found here generally chronicles Gossett’s attempts to pilot his various bills through the sub-committee and requests for the sub-committee’s attention to the immigration of specific cases/individuals. The subseries also contains published records of hearings and statements presented for hearings on various immigration bills as well as reports on bills from the committees.
    - General, 1945-1947 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1947 January-April (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1947 May-December (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Hearings, 1943-1945 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Hearings, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Hearings, 1948-1949 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Hearings, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Reports, 1943-1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Immigration and Naturalization Service, 1944-1950; 4
    This subseries relates to the United States Immigration and Naturalization Service (INS) during the years 1945-1950. Included are several memos criticizing the application or enforcement of immigration laws by the INS. The subseries also contains issues of the Monthly Review by the INS, as well as annual reports for 1944-1950 excluding 1947. In addition it contains an undated and incomplete report on immigration figures and a report on an internal investigation of an INS Assistant Chief heading seamen and smuggling work in the Investigation Section.
    - Internal Investigation, 1949 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Memos on INS Code Enforcement, 1946-1949 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Publications, 1945-1947 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Reports, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Reports, Annual, 1944 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Reports, Annual, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Reports, Annual, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Reports, Annual, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Reports, Annual, 1949 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Reports, Annual, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Interstate Freight, 1937-1949; 4
  This series contains materials dealing with the “freight rate problem” and efforts to reduce the inequality of freight rates between Texas and the Official Zone. It contains letters to Gossett, and reports for Congress beginning with a 1937 report on freight rates by the TVA and several reports from 1943 by the Board of Investigation and Research. Furthermore, it includes speeches by Gossett from 1943-1945, and a copy of his bill H.R. 413 introduced January 3, 1945, to amend the Interstate Commerce Act.
  - General, 1945-1949 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Publications, 1943-1944 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Reports, 1937-1943 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Reports, 1943 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Reports, 1945 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Speeches, 1943-1945 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Oil Industry, 1939-1951; 5
  This series relates to the issue of adequate oil supply to matters of pricing controls, taxation, pipeline infrastructure, and Middle Eastern oil. Correspondence from 1943 to 1946 deals with the rationing and price control of oil by the Office of Price Administration. Letters from 1949 to 1951 speak to the issue of assuring adequate stocks of domestic and imported oil. Other materials include reports and articles on Middle Eastern oil production, publications on the oil industry in general, and statements before the House Ways and Means Committee on price controls, taxation, and depletion allowances. Finally, it includes speeches and remarks by Gossett.
  - General, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1946 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1951 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Middle East Oil, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Middle East Oil, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Hearings, 1950 February (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Hearings, 1951 March (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Hearings, undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Publications, 1944-1949 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Publications, 1950-1951 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Speeches, 1939-1949 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Palestine, 1934-1951; 6
  This series contains materials relating to events, policies, and attitudes about Palestine following World War II. The largest portion comprises publications on the partition of Palestine and the creation of an Israeli state from the perspective of Arabs, Jews, and Americans. It also contains some UN documents from the fall of 1948 preceding the UN resolution to partition Palestine and speeches by Gossett opposing US support for the partition.
  - General, 1945-1951; 1
    This subseries pertains to Palestine following World War II and the early stages of the modern state of Israel. They include letters about Palestine and Israel, and publications about conditions in the state of Israel. Also included are several speeches by Gossett opposing the partition of Palestine for the creation of an Israeli state, in addition to speeches by others before the House of Representatives on the same topic.
    - General, 1945-1949 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1947-1951 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Israel, 1948-1950 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Speeches and Resolutions, 1946-1948 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - American Attitudes, 1934-1951; 2
    This subseries contains pamphlets, circulars, newspaper articles, and open letters that capture some American attitudes towards Palestine and the creation of an Israeli states containing arguments against an Israeli state whose content is substantively anti-Semitic from materials that are generally against Zionism or the creation of an Israeli state. The subseries also contains materials created by the American Council for Judaism which argued against an Israeli state from a Jewish perspective. Finally, pro-Zionist materials comprises letters with resolutions, newspaper ads, and pamphlets in support of an Israeli state as well as several issues of the weekly The Answer and the newspaper B’nai B’rith Messenger.
    - Anti-Semitism, 1934-1947 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Anti-Zionism, 1944-1948 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Anti-Zionism, American Council for Judaism, 1947-1951 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Pro-Zionism, 1947 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Pro-Zionism, 1948, 1951 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Middle East Relations, 1947-1951; 3
    These materials describe relations between different political actors in the Middle East both prior to but mainly after World War II. It includes news articles on combat incidents between Jews and ArabsDLthe bulk of which are found in issues of Haganah Speaks ranging from March to August 1948. Other materials include articles, newspaper articles, periodicals, booklets, and speeches describing relations between Jews and Arabs in Palestine more generally. Newspaper clippings and issues of The Answer and Haganah Speaks discuss British involvement in Palestine. Finally, this subseries contains newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and radio addresses on American foreign policy in Palestine.
    - Arab-Jewish Combat, 1947-1950 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Arab-Jewish Relations, 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Arab-Jewish Relations, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Arab-Jewish Relations, 1949-1950 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - United Kingdom and Palestine, 1947-1948 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - United States and Palestine, 1946-1948 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - United States and Palestine, 1948-1951 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - United Nations Partition, 1947-1948; 4